<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Uncategorized | Dude, where's my Kaizen?]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/blog/categories/uncategorized/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/"/>
  <updated>2011-11-06T22:55:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Björn Rochel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm doing the T-thing now, too]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/12/10/im-doing-the-t-thing-now-too/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-10T19:33:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/12/10/im-doing-the-t-thing-now-too</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Although I'm still not 100% sure that I "get" what the Twitter fuzz is all about, I decided to give it a try and use it for a while, in order
to form my opinion about it. If you're interested to stay in touch via Twitter, here's my Url:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twitter.com/BjoernRochel">http://www.twitter.com/BjoernRochel</a></p>

<p>Cheerz Björn</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's next?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/11/30/whats-next/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-30T10:56:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/11/30/whats-next</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the "Diving into the StoryTeller trunk series" coming to an end in the near future, I'm currently looking into several ideas for future
posts. Here's what I'm currently thinking about:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>xUnit.BDDExtensions feature walkthrough and documentation</strong> Let's be honest it's currently not documented at all. I failed big time at
documenting its usage scenarios and behavior so far. However, since more and more projects at my current client are starting to use it I'm
definitely going to fix this . . .</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Look into various options to implement the Active Object Pattern</strong> I've been reading several papers
about infrastructures for command execution lately. It's an interesting topic for distributed scenarios (for instance used in a CQSR design),
but also for local scenarios when you start to think about multi core / concurrent programming. As modern applications are becoming more and
more connected on the one hand and need to use local resources more efficiently on the other (because processors won't get a lot faster in
the near future) I think there's a huge need for having a simple consistent design for both. Things I'd like to look into are the
Concurrency Coordination Runtime, the .NET 4.0 Task Parallel Library and Application Spaces, as well as more specific topics like integrating
such an infrastructure with an MVVM design.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Dive into the Caliburn trunk</strong> Last but not least I would love to spend some time with Caliburn
since WPF is more and more on my radar and Caliburn seems to fully embrace and extend a lot of the original WPF design ideas in a composite
context. I think I would do something similar to the StoryTeller series.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>So, what do you think? Any preferences? Any priorities?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yes, I'm still alive . . .]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/01/19/yes-im-still-alive/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-19T13:06:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/01/19/yes-im-still-alive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First of all: Happy new year to everyone. I know, I know, I'm really late with that :-)</p>

<p>It's been really quite on this blog for the last two month and I'm sorry for that. I've been busy changing a lot of things that caused me
frustration and friction in my life as a software engineer in 2008 ...</p>

<p>Anyway, 2009, a new year. What's to expect from this blog this year?</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Ruby</strong> Following the pragmatic programmers advice I started to learn a new
language, namely Ruby. Expect to see a lot of posts around the Ruby language, the Rake buildsystem, Gems, RSpec, Ruby on Rails and
IronRuby in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Software architecture in .NET and the Ruby realm</strong>
A good, simple software design has always been one of the key aspects to successful software projects for me. This includes
testability, automation, convention-based development, reversibility, extensibility, maintainability and a lot of other
stuff. Many areas to be covered. Lots of posts to be written :-)</li>
</ol>


<p>Stay tuned for more . . .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharing book experiences]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/10/28/sharing-book-experiences/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-28T17:54:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/10/28/sharing-book-experiences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Update 21.10.2011</h2>

<p>I've moved my shelf to <a href="http://www.goodreads.com">Goodreads</a>. You can find my new shelf <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/bjoernrochel">here</a>.</p>

<p>I've read about this at Michel Grootjans Blog. Actually a very nice idea. You can find my bookshelf under:
<a href="http://www.shelfari.com/o1518053563">http://www.shelfari.com/o1518053563</a></p>

<p>Keep reading, guys :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Resharper 4.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/09/04/resharper-41/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-04T21:31:14+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/09/04/resharper-41</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cool, Jetbrains just released a new version of it's famous productivity enhancer. I'm going to update my development machine tomorrow. It's just an awesome tool . . .</p>

<p>See <a href="http://blogs.jetbrains.com/dotnet/2008/09/resharper-41-is-released/">http://blogs.jetbrains.com/dotnet/2008/09/resharper-41-is-released/</a> for more information.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
