<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Uncategorized | Dude, where's my Kaizen?]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/blog/categories/uncategorized/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/"/>
  <updated>2011-11-15T15:56:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Björn Rochel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[At the crossroads]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2011/11/15/at-the-crossroads/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-15T09:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2011/11/15/at-the-crossroads</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>512 days or 17 months or 1.5 years. That's the time between todays post and my last one.
Not as long as the Duke Nukem Forever development time, but it still strikes me how much
time has gone by since I've written something down here.</p>

<p>Today is probably going to be a very personal post and for that matter also non-technical one.</p>

<h2>So, what happened in those 512 days?</h2>

<p>First of all, 512 days ago I deliberately stopped blogging. I had lost all fun in writing.
It felt more than a burden than anything useful to me. Well I guess that had something to do
with a slowly and painful kind of burnout I experienced during my time at a large German consultancy.
It took me a while to realize what's going on with me, but in the end, I think, I made the right
decision leaving the contracting, ups sorry, I mean consulting business.</p>

<p>I've spend a lot of my free time in the last 2 years doing some form of community
work. Not via blogging, but rather by</p>

<ul>
<li>Building <a href="http://www.github.com/bjro/machine.fakes/">Machine.Fakes</a>,</li>
<li>speaking at several conferences, user groups and open spaces,</li>
<li>facilitating the F# bookclub in Munich 2010 where we worked through <a href="http://www.manning.com/petricekt/">Real-World
Functional Programming</a>,</li>
<li>and helping <a href="http://www.der-albert.com/">Albert Weinert</a> to get the <a href="http://onlineusergroup.de">.NET Online User Group</a> off the ground.</li>
</ul>


<p>Besides I helped sucesfully delivering 3 large projects in the time. Two of them exceeded the customers expectations.
One didn't. Simply put, I will never do any form of TFS customization again, never ever.</p>

<p>In mid 2010, out of curiosity, I bought my first Apple computer, a MacBook Pro. I started
to play around with it and actually liked it a lot. Guess what, I'm an IPhone and IPod owner, too.
I'm not religious about Apple products, though. They work for me and excactly deliver what
I expect and need from those devices.</p>

<p>Well, and after a while of using OSX, I began revisiting Ruby (after my initial steps in 2008) and
picked up where I left the last time. I learned the basics of using <a href="http://www.vim.org">VIM</a>,
<a href="http://www.git-scm.com">Git</a> and started to play around with <a href="http://www.rubyonrails.org">Ruby on Rails</a> and
with Rails the whole topic of web development (after having left the topic in 2003).</p>

<h2>Big changes are coming for me in 2012</h2>

<p>As you might have noticed, I've revived my blog. The design and the technology chosen might give you
an idea where this is all heading.</p>

<p>Next year I'm going to work in a new team, with non .NET technology, with a unix based OS as my primary development environment.
I'm really exited to join <a href="http://www.xing.de">XING</a> as a developer working on their <a href="http://www.rubyonrails.org">Ruby on Rails</a> based
platform.</p>

<p>Besides I'm planning to learn a new (non .NET) programming language next year, that currently feels completely alien to me, namely <a href="http://www.clojure.org">Clojure</a>.
If everything goes as planned we're going to re-use the bookclub format we used in 2010 for the F# bookclub in Munich, though
in a somewhat virtualized form, and try to get into the <a href="http://www.joyofclosure.com">Joy of Clojure</a>.</p>

<p>Last but not least, I'm not nuts and discard everything I learned during the last years.
I'm probably going to play with MonoDevelop and try to learn how to build IPhone, Android, IPad and Cocoa apps using Mono.
At least that's the plan.</p>

<h2>On leaving .NET</h2>

<p>What does leaving acutally mean? Let's break this down a bit.</p>

<h3>Am I going to stop playing the active role for Machine.Fakes?</h3>

<p>Undecided, but probable since I won't be using it on a day to day basis next year.
I've ideas for re-using it under mono, but I haven't actually tried so far. We'll see ...</p>

<h3>Do I stop being in touch with parts of the .NET community?</h3>

<p>Don't be silly</p>

<h3>Do I stop visiting .NET Open Spaces or UserGroups?</h3>

<p>Well, that is at least not my plan.</p>

<h2>What, no leaving .NET rant?</h2>

<p>In the last 4 years of active community involvement I had the honour and pleasure to get
to know a great bunch of .NET developers. Talented and gifted people, from all over Germany
(and even outside Germany), each of them awesome in his own way.</p>

<p>Just to name a few <a href="http://www.twitter.com/agross">@agross</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/sforkmann">@sforkmann</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/ilkerde">@ilkerde</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/stefanlieser">@StefanLieser</a>,
<a href="http://www.twitter.com/mikebild">@mikebild</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/sshishkin">@sshishkin</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/lanwin">@lanwin</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/cdeger">@cdeger</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/oakinger">@oakinger</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/jpboodhoo">@jpboodhoo</a>,
<a href="">@kostjaklein</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/torstenweber">@torstenweber</a>, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/gregyoung">@gregyoung</a> and a lot more.  I could probably make the list a lot longer, but those are the people that managed to
leave a lasting impact on me. Thank you all!</p>

<p>The German .NET community has changed tremendously (for the good) in the time I've been
working with .NET, which is in great parts a result of the work of those people.
Moving away from focus solely on tools crafted by you know who, to embrace and teach practices/principles of
of professional software development, like SOLID, TDD/BDD/ATDD, Continuous Integration, Continuous Delivery, et al.</p>

<p>Microsoft (at least in my opinion) has also changed a lot (well at least in some areas, thank you ASP.NET team!).
They're hosting code at publicly available locations, they're accepting patches from the outside and they actually listen
carefully to community feedback. They still got a lot to improve, but hey, I wouldn't believed you if you'd told me 4 years ago how parts of MS engage with
the community today.</p>

<h3>Why a technology change?</h3>

<p>Change often implies frustration or dissatisfaction with something. I want this
to be as clear as possible: <strong>Those are not my primary reasons</strong>.</p>

<p>I'm going to tell you a little secret right now, well sort of. Some of my older colleagues
know this, some still don't:</p>

<p><strong>I never owned a computer before my 21st birthday. I didn't even write a program till I was 22.</strong></p>

<p>Let that sink in for a moment.  Nevertheless, I somehow managed to leave every company I've worked for
in the the last 10 years with the impression that I was one of the top software
developers they ever worked with.</p>

<p>I often wondered how I managed to pull that off, but I guess it boils down to this: I really, really, really badly want to be
good at what I'm doing (whatever that is) and am willing to work as hard as necessary in order to reach that goal. I've had
my ups and downs with this strategy, but in the end it made me how I am and helped me to get where I am today. I honestly believe that you
can achieve much more than you might think, if you step out of what comforts you as often as possible
(though some people prefer to tell you the opposite and are very resistant with that).</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If you remain in your comfort zone you will not go any further</p><footer><strong>Catherine Pulsifer</strong><cite></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><strong>If</strong> you're passionate about what you do, <strong>if</strong> you put yourself in the
mood that you basically know nothing and that you can learn (in one way or another)
from nearly anybody around you, <strong>if</strong> you accept that you will fail in one
way or another and failing is ok if and only if you learn from failure,
and last but not least <strong>if</strong> you accept that for the most of us being good at something
actually is the result of continuous learning, hard work, deliberate practice and experience (as
opposed to talent only), <strong> than you define what's possible for you and not somebody else.</strong></p>

<p>I'd like to think about myself as a developer, not as a C# developer, not as a OO
developer, not as an ASP.NET developer, nor Javascript developer for that matters.
Developer, just developer. Building awesome products in teams is my passion, but not building
awesome products with technlogy X,Y or Z. Languages, technlogies are <strong>part of my toolset, not something I'm
married to</strong> till death tears us apart.</p>

<p>Number 1 reason for making a technology change is that I want to extend my personal toolset</p>

<h3>Is that all?</h3>

<p>It's no big secret that being an engaged person that likes to think outside the
box and not limits his views to the Microsoft way of building software, can
sometimes have a hard time in the Microsoft ecosystem (especially if you like to
work with teams and don't want to go down the independent consultant road).</p>

<p>It's utterly frustrating to hear from Microsoft evangelists that you're not part
of the target group for their product (!!! Visual Studio !!!) if you ask for
more extensibility and less re-implementations of existing open source solutions
(No shit, that really happened to me 1 month ago and I still can't believe they
actually said that).</p>

<p>I like the .NET framework and I especially like C#, but I'm more and
more frustrated with their sales driven approach to software development.  The frustrating part is that in
the end I can understand why they bundle/entangle their products from a sales perspective.
It's probably my fault for not realizing earlier that this somewhat clashes
with my slightly opinionated approach to building software.</p>

<p>I sometimes tend to think that a greater part of us (of the .NET community)
would live a lot happier professional live outside the MS ecosystem and those
of us that do manage to pull that off inside that MS ecosystem have build
themselves <strong>a beautiful oasis in a vast and wide desert</strong>.</p>

<p>My current  project team is an example of the latter, using a mix of techniques from
Lean, ATDD , BDD, with feature branching and extensive code review sessions.
And all that is possible without the TFS and without 80% of the features of Visual
Studio. Who would have thought that ...</p>

<p>However this team is breaking apart at the end of the year and I'm in the
position to start something new next year.  Trying to get a new .NET team
to the same state (or above) was an option, but I decided against that. Instead I
decided to venture into new territory, to extend my toolkit with
a new language and a new platform.</p>

<h3>Why Ruby?</h3>

<p><blockquote><p>I skate to where the puk is going to be, not where it has been</p><footer><strong>Wayne Gretzky</strong><cite></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I really, really like the quote, I really do, but do I think Ruby is the next
big thing?</p>

<p><strong>Honestly, I don't</strong></p>

<p>I don't say this in any negative way.  At the end of the end of the day
Ruby is just a tool (though awesome tool) that can be used,
misused and abused for getting things done.</p>

<p>What I'm more interested in is the Ruby community itself or even more
precise the state of engineering practices in the community. From the outside
they look far ahead than the common denominator in the Microsoft world.  Lots and lots of
.NET OSS frameworks and tools have been influenced by the Ruby community
in one way or another.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The Moslems have a proverb,  to understand a man, you've got to walk a mile in his shoes, whether they fit or not.</p><footer><strong>Raymond Wiley Miller</strong><cite>1964</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The Ruby community seems to be a great starting point for my venture.
Lots of innovation going on, lots of passion involved, very OSS centered
and goal orientated.  However, I will never know for sure if those expectations
hold up to the reality unless I work amongst them for a while ...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm doing the T-thing now, too]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/12/10/im-doing-the-t-thing-now-too/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-10T19:33:32+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/12/10/im-doing-the-t-thing-now-too</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Although I'm still not 100% sure that I "get" what the Twitter fuzz is all about, I decided to give it a try and use it for a while, in order
to form my opinion about it. If you're interested to stay in touch via Twitter, here's my Url:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.twitter.com/BjoernRochel">http://www.twitter.com/BjoernRochel</a></p>

<p>Cheerz Björn</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's next?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/11/30/whats-next/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-30T10:56:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/11/30/whats-next</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the "Diving into the StoryTeller trunk series" coming to an end in the near future, I'm currently looking into several ideas for future
posts. Here's what I'm currently thinking about:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>xUnit.BDDExtensions feature walkthrough and documentation</strong> Let's be honest it's currently not documented at all. I failed big time at
documenting its usage scenarios and behavior so far. However, since more and more projects at my current client are starting to use it I'm
definitely going to fix this . . .</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Look into various options to implement the Active Object Pattern</strong> I've been reading several papers
about infrastructures for command execution lately. It's an interesting topic for distributed scenarios (for instance used in a CQSR design),
but also for local scenarios when you start to think about multi core / concurrent programming. As modern applications are becoming more and
more connected on the one hand and need to use local resources more efficiently on the other (because processors won't get a lot faster in
the near future) I think there's a huge need for having a simple consistent design for both. Things I'd like to look into are the
Concurrency Coordination Runtime, the .NET 4.0 Task Parallel Library and Application Spaces, as well as more specific topics like integrating
such an infrastructure with an MVVM design.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Dive into the Caliburn trunk</strong> Last but not least I would love to spend some time with Caliburn
since WPF is more and more on my radar and Caliburn seems to fully embrace and extend a lot of the original WPF design ideas in a composite
context. I think I would do something similar to the StoryTeller series.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>So, what do you think? Any preferences? Any priorities?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yes, I'm still alive . . .]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/01/19/yes-im-still-alive/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-19T13:06:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2009/01/19/yes-im-still-alive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First of all: Happy new year to everyone. I know, I know, I'm really late with that :-)</p>

<p>It's been really quite on this blog for the last two month and I'm sorry for that. I've been busy changing a lot of things that caused me
frustration and friction in my life as a software engineer in 2008 ...</p>

<p>Anyway, 2009, a new year. What's to expect from this blog this year?</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Ruby</strong> Following the pragmatic programmers advice I started to learn a new
language, namely Ruby. Expect to see a lot of posts around the Ruby language, the Rake buildsystem, Gems, RSpec, Ruby on Rails and
IronRuby in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Software architecture in .NET and the Ruby realm</strong>
A good, simple software design has always been one of the key aspects to successful software projects for me. This includes
testability, automation, convention-based development, reversibility, extensibility, maintainability and a lot of other
stuff. Many areas to be covered. Lots of posts to be written :-)</li>
</ol>


<p>Stay tuned for more . . .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharing book experiences]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/10/28/sharing-book-experiences/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-28T17:54:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.bjoernrochel.de/2008/10/28/sharing-book-experiences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Update 21.10.2011</h2>

<p>I've moved my shelf to <a href="http://www.goodreads.com">Goodreads</a>. You can find my new shelf <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/bjoernrochel">here</a>.</p>

<p>I've read about this at Michel Grootjans Blog. Actually a very nice idea. You can find my bookshelf under:
<a href="http://www.shelfari.com/o1518053563">http://www.shelfari.com/o1518053563</a></p>

<p>Keep reading, guys :-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
